<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cheirexokē [sic] the excellency or handy-vvork of the royal hand.</title>
            <author>Allen, Thomas, d. 1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23652</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1159</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12305775</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12305775</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59244</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23652)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59244)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 198:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cheirexokē [sic] the excellency or handy-vvork of the royal hand.</title>
                  <author>Allen, Thomas, d. 1684.</author>
                  <author>Harris, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Godbid for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title transliterated from Greek.</note>
                  <note>"The epistle dedicatory" signed: T.A., M.D.</note>
                  <note>Written by Dr. Thomas Allen. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing. Cf. also Wm. Beckett's Enquiry in the antiquity and efficacy of touching for the king's evil, 1722, p. 58: "Dr. Thomas Allen, sometime of Caius College in Cambridge, afterward physician in ordinary to King Charles the Second, published a treatise of the cure of the evil by the touch, which he entitles, 'The excellency or handy-work of the royal hand'." BM attributes to either Allen or to Thomas Harris.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59244:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΧΕΙΡΕΞΟΚΗ</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>THE EXCELLENCY OR HANDY-VVORK OF The Royal Hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Godbid</hi> for the Author. M.DC.LXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59244:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59244:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Puiſſant and Illuſtrious PRINCE IAMES Duke of <hi>YORK</hi> and <hi>ALBANIE,</hi> LORD of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LTONE,</hi> LORD CHIEF ADMIRALL of ENGLAND, AND KNIGHT of the moſt Renowned and Noble Order of the GARTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>ROYAL SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I am of my ſelf a Subject inconſiderable, yet that which I here adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to treat of, is of more worth. And, in good earneſt, I ſhould not have been reconciled to my ſelf with the Dedication, had I not laid
<pb facs="tcp:59244:3"/>a ſtrict injunction upon it, in the firſt place, to viſit the beſt of Families, that of Yours; to whom I owe not only my ſelf, but all I have in the world. The Excellency in this Treatiſe is the Subject, otherwiſe (I muſt confeſs) twere much beneath your Highneſs countenance, <hi>cui majora debeantur:</hi> Yet, 'tis Golden chaffer, Sir, and if but ſtamp'd with your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Acceptance, 'twill paſs Currant, and I ſhall expoſe it to the ſurging bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of a Tempeſtuous World. 'Tis plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> without any intermixture but what is meerly neceſſary; 'tis clad (for the moſt part) in its Mother Tongue, yet a little <hi>French</hi> puts it into the mode, and gives it a kind of Reputation. I thought it my Duty to invoke your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Patronage; pardon my Ambition in it, and receive it as a pledge, and the
<pb facs="tcp:59244:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>effect of abundance of regards towards You; and if your Highneſs judge aright, they may be weigh'd in the ballance with your greateſt Admirers. Theſe Conceptions are the true Iſſue of my Heart, as well as my Invention: Be pleaſed to caſt but as kind an Eye upon them, as you have in your Infancy almoſt (as I may ſay) done upon the Author; but Time which hath worn out all things, hath him too out of your Remembrance. That which may be the greateſt inducement to your Highneſs to read this ſmall Product, is the Centre to which it truly points, and may be (God knows how ſoon) your own concern. 'Tis an old Art, but new reviv'd; 'tis the Refining and Sublimating of <hi>LOYALTY</hi> to ſuch a pitch as may render it Guſtfull, and all (if poſſible) after long Seducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to their due Obedience to their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:59244:4"/>
               <hi>PRINCE.</hi> And being banded by ſo good Authority, as indeed it is, it needs no Licence for its Publication, and your Highneſs cannot but give it a Careſs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours moſt affectionately devoted to Love and Revere You with all due Obſervance <hi>T.A.</hi> M.D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59244:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE EXCELLENCY <hi>or</hi> HANDY VVORK OF THE Royal Hand.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot but take notice, that for ſeveral years laſt paſt, divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, taking the advantage of there being no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> have hugg'd themſelves too much, with the vain hopes of having Fortune to be their Miſtriſs, whom they more courted for Succeſs, than the Deity, boaſting themſelves the ſeventh Sons, Stroakers, and what not, have become great Undertakers, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by their manual Touch, the perfect Cure of thoſe Swellings, commonly called by the name of the <hi>Kings Evil. Aegris &amp; aſtantibus mirabilia pollicentur,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed more in a quarter of an hour, than they can make good all their life time: <hi>Vitam vendunt quèm longiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, ut verendum ſit nobis, nè ſero nimis in calum redeamus:</hi> Their ſelf-conceitedneſs, and proud blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59244:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>has emboldned them to ſo high a pitch, that they have adventured upon thoſe things which they had neither competent ſtrength to wield, nor any warrant from God Almighty to attempt, and the more ignorant the more confident; thus have they hook'd in ſimple Credulity to worſhip their Idolatry, and admire their Enthuſiaſms; they have fiſh'd for a Name and Fame amongſt the caſie deceived vulgar, who loſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the miſt of ſuch mens Ignorance. Thus have they fallen upon Practice, which has prov'd ſo fatal a fall to many of them, that they could never riſe to any thing after; having deluded thoſe which were too big with belief, and apt to receive that for a ſpark of Truth (their Reaſon being dim-ſighted) that lay bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in a heap of Errours.</p>
            <p>That many things in this Evil Malady are really ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by Topical Medicaments, the Authority of moſt eminent Phyſicians, and none of the meaneſt Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, will make good, and induce us to credit, whoſe undoubted Experience muſt not be contradicted, nor repugned. That indeed which they have profeſſed themſelves potent to effect, by a Touch, and ſolely upon this account, becauſe they are the Seventh Sons, has been the <hi>Kings Evil;</hi> but who has faith enough to believe this to be natural? for that which is natural hath its dependence on the moſt inward Principles, and on every <hi>Individuum</hi> of the ſame <hi>Species:</hi> but this muſt not be granted, neither doth it depend on the number, for according to the Axioms of Philoſophy, a number hath no operative vertue, and likewiſe <hi>Actiones ſunt Suppoſitorum,</hi> All Actions are the Products of the <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum,</hi> and have their Shore upon the form of things;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59244:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>but the Seventh Son is ſaid to have that peculiar power which the other Six are deprived of, and only <hi>quatenus</hi> the Seventh. Therefore being it proceeds neither ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the premiſes, from the form, nor number, it muſt neceſſarily, were it ſo, have its riſe elſewhere; to which I ſhall ſpeak more home after a little further progreſs. Many Families, in the time of the Apoſtles, did abound with a numerous Off-ſpring: yet 'tis not upon Record, neither before the Infancy of Chriſtian Religion, nor ſince, that any of the Seventh Sons did ever make any contention with them, touching the power of working theſe miracles. The Subject, is The Operator, the Practiſer of this Myſterie, to wit, <hi>A Gracious King,</hi> who for Clemency exceeds all the Pious and potent Monarchs that ever liv'd before Him, whoſe Pardon, before I can proceed, I am here with all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to beg, that I make him again a Subject, being ſo lately too long one. The Object, is the Evil Subject, the <hi>Kings Evil.</hi> As for the <hi>Signum Pathognomonicum,</hi> 'tis ſo obvious to the Eye, and Touch, that I think it impertinent to touch at all upon that String, whereby (like <hi>Ariadnes</hi> Clue) to direct you to the knowledge of it: Yet becauſe I will not leave you in the dark, I ſhall endevour to decipher theſe Swellings in their true and proper colours.</p>
            <p>They are called <hi>Strumae,</hi> which are <hi>Glandulae indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratae, quas Graeci</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>vocant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Arabians, Scrofulae, in collo plerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> collocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> they are cauſed from Phlegm conſolidated in the glandulous parts; ſome <hi>Tuberculae magnae;</hi> ſome <hi>parvae,</hi> which are with more facility cur'd. I would not be thought one of thoſe, that tearm Good, Evil; and Evil,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59244:6"/>Good: Yet there are degrees, I would, if poſſible, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you with ſo much inſight, as that you may be able to diſtinguiſh betwixt them. Some are, like His Majeſties Subjects, ſome better conditioned than others, yet ſome attended with ſo much Malignity, that they will not admit of any cure but what is palliative; <hi>Quaedam quaſi ſuſpenſae huc &amp; illucfacile moventur,</hi> they move to and fro, and yet are not eaſily removed; <hi>quaedam inſertae oriantur,</hi> and are frequently diſſeminated clean though the Veſſels, as Veins, and Arteries; They are for the moſt part Tumours, conſiſting of Equality, neither ſoft nor hard, but of a <hi>medium</hi> betwixt both: The <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheria</hi> round, and it has been generally obſerved, that thoſe perſons which have been moſt affected with it, either they themſelves, or ſome of their neareſt Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, have been all along for the moſt part Round, as the World has gone too long, <hi>Sublata cauſa tollitur effectus.</hi> The Cure of all Diſeaſes is wrought by a depulſion of the Cauſe. <hi>Tactus, quaſi Tactus, vim habet ſolam Tangendi;</hi> The Touch, as Touch, hath only the power of Touching: Otherwiſe by conſequence, that certain virtue which is in the body, were it noxious, would alſo by the ſame Touch be communicated, but the Touch it ſelf hath not this virtue: Seeing then that other Diſeaſes may proceed from one and the ſame Cauſe, in ſome other parts of the body, the ſame Touch might prove Energetical for their removal; but being it cannot be ſo, the Cure muſt either be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous, or wholly attributed to the Imagination of the Patient; but we cannot believe it to be miraculous, for in times paſt the Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtians, both for the further Illuſtrating of God's Glory, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59244:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>augmenting of Chriſtian Religion, <hi>manuum impoſitione multos ſanârunt,</hi> have healed many by a Touch; and moſt true it is, God will not have miracles inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately wrought, for the pleaſure of any man; So that the Apoſtles have ſignified to us, that, That which they did, was not by their own power, or by virtue and power of the Touch, and in their own ſtrength, but by the Indulgence and ſpecial Mandate of the Great <hi>Jehovah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore thoſe Seven Sons of <hi>Shevah</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> who attempting by the ſame name, to conjure the Devils, have, by induring their horrid violence, ſufficiently felt the puniſhment of their temerarious, and unadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed boldneſs: Hence we may conclude, That 'tis not lawful for ordinary perſons to aſſume ſo great a power, their skill in healing is not the Gift of God, as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by the quality of the perſons, who are generally ignorant, and prophane; for which very cauſe, God will not reveal his Counſels to them, but to them that truly fear him: 'Tis true, if it be his pleaſure, he can bring Good out of Evil. There are in the world, too many of theſe prodigious and ſeducing Juglers, which do probably ſome ſmall inconſiderable things; Theſe <hi>Simple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons,</hi> through the pretence and reputation of Divine power, may cure ſome ſimple wounds which only requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Union, which Nature would have done her ſelf. Thus they daily make a noiſe, with their forged miracles, and make any Truth of any falſhood, be it never ſo notorious, and a prejudicated opinion of ſuch mens ſuppoſed ſufficiency, they themſelves being not really able to diſcern betwixt right and wrong, Good and Evil; they are great Uſurpers upon other mens Rights,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59244:7"/>againſt whom I ſhall advance the Avant-guard of all my might and force, not only to batter, but totally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat, depreſs, and lay theſe evil Spirits, who have no more dangerous ſnare, than this condition of Faith, that thoſe who will have help or ſuccour at their hands, muſt believe they can do them good.</p>
            <p>As to the Imagination, it being divers, in ſome fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, in ſome weaker, we may ſuppoſe nothing, but an uncertain Event, can be expected from an uncertain Cauſe. The unreaſonable part of Fancy juggles too much with the judgments and underſtandings of men, that they can ſcarce contain themſelves from believing, and conſulting with ſome ridiculous folly: thus able is Imagination not only to deceive ſenſe, but obſcure our Reaſon. If there be any good which the World fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in them, they have it by Accident, by the power and virtue of Fancy, wherein is neither certainty nor continuance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoc privilegium ſanandi ſtrumas, eſt</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>divinum planè munus;</hi> The power of Curing this Evil, is vouchſafed ſolely to the Kings, by the Grace of God, of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and denied to other Chriſtian Kings; <hi>non proprietaete perſonarum, ſed Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no privilegio; non verborum tantum facultate, nec medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum auxilio, ſed conſtantis fidei, &amp; vehementis cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis vi, ſanitas ſperetur.</hi> 'Tis a Legacy bequeathed to then, by God himſelf. Holy <hi>Remigius,</hi> a Reverend Biſhop in <hi>France,</hi> with whoſe Unction this power flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> as the beſt Interpreter, doubtleſs, of this matter, hath declared, That this excellent Virtue is granted to Kings, ſo long as they ſhall remain conſtant in the Chriſtian Faith; intimating,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59244:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>It would ceaſe if they forſook, or fell from it; and ſo long as Faith remained either in King or Kingdom, he foretold, by the Spirit of Prophecie, he ſhould be a victorious King: But alas, his Divinity here fail'd him! for, not long before our diſtractions in <hi>England,</hi> we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſiſtant to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> were much worſted; of which ſayes one, and not impertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<q>
                  <l>When Wars in <hi>England</hi> once began</l>
                  <l>Then flouriſh'd <hi>France,</hi> and not till than.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Picardie</hi> was moſt part of it in a Flame; the Scene was laid by Cardinal <hi>Richelieu</hi> to introduce the <hi>Scots,</hi> he had all the qualities requiſite to work a change of State, by his prudence the Stroke was diverted, he directed his deſigns to make that Nation flouriſh, which he lived to ſee effected; thoſe that have but the leaſt Spark of Love for the Glory of that Country, when they read but that name, it muſt needs raiſe in them, an eſteem, never to be forgotten. <hi>Edward the Confeſſor,</hi> that had the reputation of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Piety, was deemed by the People one that could work Miracles, he cured not only thoſe (which privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge deſcended to his Succeſſors) but other Ulcers and Swellings, which his Succeſſors could not. This being therefore a Prerogative belonging only to the fore-mentioned Kings, is wholly wrought in the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; it would therefore be a too audacious tempting of Providence, for other Kings, on whom ſhe would not graciouſly beſtow the gift, to attempt it. Further, 'tis worth the obſervance, That
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59244:8"/>the Kings to whom God granted it, had it not been upon condition, that they would not tranſmit this power to their Succeſſors, unleſs they were legitimate, and did remain ſtable in the Chriſtian Faith. For if an Aſſaſſinate or an Uſurper (ſuch there have been too late, and God knows what Fates yet attend King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms) ſhould dethrone a lawful Prince, he could not (together with his Kingdoms) acquire this virtue. <hi>Quippe pro Imperio,</hi> though <hi>Cromwel</hi> durſt do any thing, and wrought no leſſe then Miracles, for his time, he never ſo much as offered at this.</p>
            <p>That good King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of ever bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, when captivated by thoſe imparallel'd Miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, as his manner was, and as Tokens of his great love to many that had not deſerved that kindneſs at his hands, he cured the Evil, ſmall pieces of Silver was his gift, for alas he could not arrive to others, 'twas not the golden Age with him. I ſhall rehearſe a Story, and a very true one, not long before he Acted his laſt on that horrid and execrable Theatre. A Great Anti-Royaliſt and Committee-man, had one only Child, a Daughter about ten years of Age, which was ſo blind for a year and a half together, with her Fathers Evil, I may rather tearm it then any ones elſe, that ſhe could not ſee at all, <hi>non minus morborum quàm poſſeſſionum haeredes, Naturae ſequitur ſemina quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuae.</hi> She was brought to <hi>Kings-Hatfield</hi> in <hi>Hertford-ſhire,</hi> to the Right Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able the Earl of <hi>Salisburie</hi>'s houſe, where His Majeſty then was, and deſired a Touch from His Sacred hand, which was done by Special Grace and Favour in one of the Gardens, towards the Evening; the next morning, ſhe began to perceive a glimmering of light, that could
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59244:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>not before diſtinguiſh the day from the night, but was conſtrained to be led conſtantly about the houſe by a Maid Servant: The Father finding ſo much bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and ſeeing relief at hand, became an earneſt Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner for another Touch, which His Majeſty (that he might complete the Miracle) preſently vouchſafed; by the next morning, ſhe was reſtored to her perfect ſight. The Good man (I give him now that Epithete) her Father (becauſe he proved ſo after) finding ſo much efficacy, ſo much of God in His Anointed, he forthwith began to burſt out into tears, and accurſe himſelf, and own him that he had diſowned ſo long. The truth of all which is to be made out by perſons of quality, with divers of inferiour degree, which ought to be credited, being of good Life and Converſation. One remarkable ſtory more I ſhall treſpaſs upon your patience to repeat, being more conciſe then the laſt.</p>
            <p>A Child of a Gentlewomans of no mean worth, about Seven years old, being very infirm and evilly diſpos'd, having received a Touch in the morning, in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon one of the Serjeant Chyrurgeons, having a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard for the Mother, came to give it a Viſit. The Child he found leaning againſt a Couch in the Room; caſually taking a few Peaſe out of his Pocket, which he uſed to employ in Fontanels, he troll'd them along the Floor, whereupon the Child (taking them to be Plums) immediately made a ſhift to go after them, and took them up, which for ſome years before was ſeldome out of Arms, and in a very ſhort time grew a great Commander of his Legs; This I aver, and from as good hands as the former. And ſhould I go to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and ſumme up all thoſe Miracles (for I dare
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59244:9"/>not call them leſſe) that have been wrought by that Pattern of true Piety; A Prince whereof the World was not worthy; the beſt of all Chriſtian Kings, now undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly in Heaven, their number would be as admirable as their nature. But alas! <hi>Envy</hi> too oft attends upon a ſhining merit:yet virtue will ſtill be virtue in deſpite of Fate; though they ſurreptitiouſly took away his earthly emoluments, and his Life into the bargain, they could not take the honour of this from him that gave it, nor the right thereof, from him that received it; the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens would not ſo much blaſpheme their Maker: As the Fire of their wrath was too ſevere, ſo that of their Zeal, was much more; They were Divels certainly, that breathed in no other Element, then that of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of and barbarous Immanities; they ran headlong in a graceleſſe method; their Union was nought, but Conſpiracy; their Strength, Outrage; their Hearts were too obdurate, forgetting all Pity, and Juſtice too; He became a Martyr for the Peoples offences, having few of his own, which he was not ſo much guilty of, as his Nature. Here fell a matchleſs peice of Innocency, meerly crucified to the tranſgreſſion of the times; we were too remiſs in our duties to Him, for which we have as much cauſe to requeſt God's Pardon, as now his Son's our Dread and Dear Soveraign Lord the King; 'tis far better to be ſubject to our true born Prince, rather than to Tyranny and Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>God be bleſſed for it, he is <hi>Rex hominum.</hi> His People will (I hope) obey him in any reaſonable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, being ſufficiently convinced, that he will not require that at their hands, but what may become the Spirit of amoſt Excellent Prince to demand, and Loyal
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59244:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Subjects to grant, may we be readier to give than He is to ask, at leaſt to yeild due Allegiance to Him, whereby to gratifie the Candour, and Goodneſs of a too too much injur'd Patience.</p>
            <p>This Treatiſe is writ with an Intention to undeceive the World, and that Wiſe men may decline thoſe vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Errours, not follow after meer ſhadowes, and loſe the Subſtance, thoſe ſtroaking Undertakers being war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted neither by Holy Writ, nor awful Authority of Antiquity or Probability of Reaſon; they are in the Judgment of the World, like our New lights, which like an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> or <hi>Will with a Wiſp,</hi> makes men run into ſuch a Labyrinth, that they run themſelves both out of what they have, and their Wits to boot. Truth does not alwayes receive a juſt tryal, by caſual Events. Hap, is a meer Paralogiſme, a Fallacy, and grand De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, taking that for a true Cauſe, which is no cauſe indeed. Eaſe may ſometimes be given, and the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of it to thoſe that do not deſerve it. Opinion weighs much, 'tis true, and Kings are great Rarities, Seventh Sons are not. That which God doth beſtow upon Kings, ſhould be that, which both for the Rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Singularity of the Priviledge, might more manifeſt his Glory; which would not be, if he ſhould attribute the ſame thing, and that by right of birth, to any other. But to deal candidly and ingenuouſly with you, 'tis thus. This Diſeaſe of the Evil, is more proper to children, than any other, which by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of years, by reaſon of heat, is many times diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated, and hereupon iſlues a ſpontaneous ceſlation thereof, which is uſual with many of thoſe that are incident to Children; and if thus it is effected, 'tis not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59244:10"/>to be attributed to the uncertain virtue, and power, of thoſe kind of men, that Touch, who have no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion at all in them, yet entitle themſelves to it: But to Nature it ſelf, whom <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſtyles, <hi>Morborum Medicatrix,</hi> The Lady Phyſician of all Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>Me thinks true Loyaliſts ſhould ſet a conſiderable eſtimate upon the Bequeſt of a dead Soveraign; Let not a Jewel of ſo much worth be bangled away; ſhould we, 'twould be an evident ſigne, we want that love for him which we truly ought to have, and that we caſt an Eye of Contempt as well upon him as his Gift. 'Tis a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, intruſted with our now Soveraign, for an Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſuch reputation were his virtues of, even in forein parts, and amongſt thoſe with whom he was by ſome deemed, (as I may ſay, I hope without offence) an Heretick, that Strangers could not enough admire Him; His very Geſture was a Net, to catch their Good Wills.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exegit ibi monumentum aere perennius, quod nec imber edax, nec Aquilo poſſit diruere.</hi> To whoſe everlaſting Honour be it ſpoken, notwithſtanding all the Exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, that God had brought him under; all the Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, Politicks, and Fetches laid to enſnare Him; He ſtill withſtood them, and continued ſteadfaſt, being Reſident ſome years where a contrary Religion was openly profeſſed, and maintained; Home-bred Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaries there were too many, but eternal praiſes be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the King of Kings, ours was out of their reach, as to offer the leaſt violence to Him, and therefore made it their work, to reach him with their Tongues, and, if poſſible, murther Him that way, perſuading the People that He was warping towards Popery. To their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59244:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhame never to be wip'd off, be it retorted, and our Churches Glory aſſerted; He has been the ſame Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Faith, and Proteſtant Cauſe, in the midſt of the greateſt Temptations, and ſtrongeſt Adverſaries; His Title was our Fame, the Truth of it our happineſs, and will be His, for which very cauſe, as a reward of a pious Conſtancy againſt all Extremities, God wrought this for Him, the greateſt of Miracles, and yet the higheſt of Benefits, to him, and to this Nation, His Reſtauration, which has fill'd the World with aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as our Hearts with exceeding great Joy; and indeed, 'twas impoſſible, it ſhould be otherwiſe, ſo much ſtability, and Divine qualities, as He is truly endow'd with; Heaven muſt needs be fore'd to do ſome more than ordinary miraculous Act, for a Perſon on whom it had beſtowed ſo many: <hi>Bonus Princeps à Domino datur,</hi> God was His Guide abroad, the Bleſſed Star that directed Him, and the Shield that protected Him, and at laſt gave Him to us; let us bleſſe Him, for Him: Have but a Retroſpect to His Princely Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Patience, know that he might have had Forein Aid, but, <hi>ſe malle vinci ſuis Armis, quàm Alienis victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem eſſe;</hi> he rather ſat down peaceably conquer'd with His own men, then to be Conquerour with an Army of others. Theſe were Endearments, great Love on His part; if there be not a Return on ours, we are worſe than the vileſt ſort of men. God, you ſee, deſtin'd his Twelve years Exile, that He might appear to us in greater Luſtre and Tranſcendency. His Regreſs brought forth our Sun, which moving in His own Sphere, ſhines moſt gloriouſly, and riſes only to do us good, with healing in His Wings.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59244:11"/>
            <p> Plots we have had without number, laid and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the firſt Contrivers of them, but this of His Majeſties Return, was a juſt, and a real plot, upon thoſe Regicides, to bring them to condigne puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to whom I durſt once have appealed, and to their own Conſciences, if they did not more repent them of what they fail'd to do, than what they did. They boaſted themſelves, Cods Children, Saints, and what not; But alas! they were the Sons of men, and wicked men too, un-ſanctified Saints, their Actions ſpoke them. They ſhould have born a filial duty to their Lord and King. 'Tis labour in vain to endevour to diſ-joyn where God has made a firm Concatenation, tied a knot, not to be untied by frail mortality; many a good turn he has pleas'd to do us, but after His Return to us, being none of the meaneſt Bleſſings, we ought to Return to God Almighty all ſorts of Devoirs, otherwiſe we don't deſerve it. 'Twas not the Healing Convention that did it, but the great and ſacred Councels of Heaven. Let us not make our ſelves wiſer than our Maker, ſtudy not to withſtand or oppoſe what he has appear'd ſo miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in.</p>
            <p>Undoubtedly Monarchy is the moſt ſecure and moſt preſerving form of Government upon Earth. Submit your Wills to Providence, no Oracle you can better rely upon, ſhe knows what is beſt for you, yeild to it, and your reward followes you. He that rebels againſt his lawful Prince, rebels againſt his God; queſtionleſs he that would deſtroy his Soveraign, would alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his God, ſtanding in his way, ſo united are the Affairs of God and a King; he is in his Office like to Him, and ſubordinate to Him. You ſee that Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59244:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Egg of Conſpiracy is no ſooner laid, but 'tis addled; he that is omniſcient is not to learn which way ye intend to ſteer your Stratagem, but he prevents ye in it. The Divel he ſets his Emiſſaries to work, and ſits as Chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in your Magical Conventions, to render Kings contemptible, and bring them into diſgrace. The Plot's no ſooner over, but the old Serpent, he gives them over too; you ſee, they are no ſooner arreſted by the Magiſtrate, but his power immediately ceaſes, in not being able to hinder the Juſtice of the Almighty, his force is broke, he cannot reſcue them from it. They ſin againſt God in Heaven, and his Church on Earth, and therefore 'tis thought meet that they ſhould hang betwixt both, as being unworthy to enter the one, or tread longer upon the other. Theſe confident sons of <hi>Mars</hi> melted away like Snow before our Sun; ſuch is the difference betwixt proſperous wickedneſs, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted Innocency. They much miſtake, that think Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice ſleeps, when it does but wink a while at ſuch Offenders. Thoſe Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> ſome of them, have felt Gods Juſtice here, and, I have that charity for them, may they find mercy in Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Machiavel</hi> reports, in his Queſtions upon <hi>Livy</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> had once their Kings in ſuch Eſteem and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, that they thought every thing did become them that they did, and that nothing could be more diſgraceful to them, than to give any intimation that ſuch or ſuch a thing was not well done by their King, being abſolutely poſſeſs'd they could not do a-miſs; I would to God this ſo excellent a virtue, had been firſt wafted over into <hi>England,</hi> with their faſhions, and that 'twere now <hi>A la mode.</hi> 'Tis a capital Crime, and not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59244:12"/>venial, to Touch but Gods Anointed; <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſmote him, that he cut off but the hem of <hi>Sauls</hi> Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romanes</hi> would have Rebellion to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>maximum crimen:</hi> and though a King hath not <hi>ſanc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titatem vitae,</hi> yet if he have <hi>ſinctitatem unctionis,</hi> we are to honour him; he may erre and have his fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, 'tis true, yet in ſuch a caſe we are not to take up <hi>Gladium vindictae,</hi> but <hi>Scutum Patientiae;</hi> we muſt help our ſelves, not by a violence againſt him, but by a holy violence, the force of prayer with God; we muſt be in charity with him, would we be entertain'd by him, whoſe Title it is to be the Prince of Peace, we muſt live peaceably with him, we have all the reaſon in the world ſo to do. <hi>Il ne parle pas au Roy qui veut,</hi> ſayes the <hi>Monſieur:</hi> Not every one that would, may ſpeak to Kings: but ſuch is the great affability and condiſcention of ours, he deſires that the moſt deſpicable, the moſt defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the pooreſt wretch in the world, may receive Grace from him <hi>gratis:</hi> Being not long ſince perſuaded by ſome of his Chyrurgeons to confine himſelf, to Touch ſuch a certain number at a time; and being informed, that more were at the Palace gates, crying out for his ſuccour and help, he told the Chyrurgeon who was to attend the ſervice that month, That his hand was in, and that all that were there, ſhould then be received: And may it ever be in, may Gods hand guide it; here's a true generous and Religious care, Piety is his Practice, Acts of Charity, his daily exerciſe. Obſerve but with what alacrity he do's ye good; being ſenſible, that after he has deſign'd relief for you, 'twould be, in ſome degree, a horrible cruelty to deferr conferring of it: This
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59244:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Divine Priviledge being granted to him, how unwill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is he, to intercept the endowment of the King of Kings. His Compaſſion becomes a debt, and to his evil Subjects, which he duely payes. As his Arms are alwayes open to embrace us, ſo let our hearts and ſouls be alwayes wide open, in fervent ſupplications for him,
<q xml:lang="lat">Détque Deus coeptis vela ſecunda ſuis.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Whatever you have obſerved in him, that might raiſe love and admiration, is hourly augmented; every minute diſcovers in him new Treaſures, of true good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Princely magnanimity. Be gentle to him, he is ſo to you; certain and innumerable cares attend a Crown. Frown not upon him, your cordial ſmiles will be reſtorative; do not diſcompoſe ſo noble and ſo ſweet a diſpoſition, whoſe chiefeſt care it is to do ye all good, to do you honour. Behold him without prejudice, and as one on whom God has been pleaſed to ſtamp much of his own power and Authority; if we pour out our prayers for him, we ſhall reap the fruits of them, they will return into our own boſoms. We are obliged both by the Laws of God and Nature, to be ſubject to our King; we may ſee he has more than ordinary of God in him; he has a ſhrewd in-ſight into the event of things, and to foreſee futurities; there was not one Arrow in all the Quiver of malice which was not ſhot at him; you that are diſloyal, ſpend your venome; if you do not the ſooner ſpit it forth, you'l grow to ſuch a bulk, you'l burſt before your indefatigable charms, temper'd ſo much with gall, can take effect, be as bold as bitter. That Prince is truely great, that is as great in Loyalty as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59244:13"/>in Advice, being potent in Parliament, he is ſo inſconſed in the affections of his people, that he is beyond the Trains of Treaſon at home, and I hope forein hoſtility cannot pierce him.</p>
            <p>You ſee, he is not in love with that which generally moſt men are, what he has done without a Parliament and upon the ſcore of his own reputation. This Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition againſt the <hi>Dutch</hi> may fully convince you, he lays it up in ſtore for you, he parts with it freely to you, 'tis for your ſafety and peace, aſwell as his own. <hi>England</hi> was never till now in ſuch an Equipage, we may boaſt of it, and of a Navy worthy of ſuch a maſter, which ſtrikes terrour into all Nations, and begets the greateſt admiration, for which his friends may well love him, his foes may well fear him: He is one that knows not how to do otherwiſe than truly like himſelf. His incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble endowments and excellencies, have hitherto pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd him, but not you ſee from ſome commotions; yet Divine Wiſdome may think it requiſite in this life, to temper the felicity of humane Majeſty with ſome Diſtempers.</p>
            <p>I cannot but call to mind the Prediction of that moſt Religious Prince in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> That none would be more loyal to his Son, if God was pleaſed but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore him, than thoſe who, ſenſible of their errours, felt in their ſouls vehement motives to repentance, with deſires to make reparation where they have done amiſs, and that he would ſend them truly zealous to repay, with intereſt, that obedience and love to him, which was due to him. The King is now graciouſly pleaſed to look upon them, he receives them with all favour, and kindneſs, he has put a great truſt into their hands, they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59244:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>have an opportunity, and (I may ſay) a bleſſed one too, to make the words good of that bleſſed Diviner, and do good to themſelves in it; if they do not improve it, they were bad, very bad before, but now they will be thought ten times worſe. I hope his Majeſties Lenity has brought them into their right minds, and that they are come to themſelves again, in good earneſt 'tis high time they ſhould; by their Action now, the prints of their former Revolts may be quite obliterated: Victory 'tis true is in the power of the Almighty, and not in the hands of the inſolent; thoſe High and Mighty <hi>Hogin Mogins,</hi> who owe an Obligation to <hi>England,</hi> for their firſt being: but all our good neighborhood hath bin perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, better fruit uſes to ſpring from the tree of Gratitude, theirs is turn'd into Preſumption; as for Incouragement, theſe Commanders have enough, being the very ſame, and having ſucceſs under Uſurpation, 'tis impoſſible for them to want it, under their lawful Soveraign; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to animate them, they have Scripture to back them, Gods promiſes, the haughty he will humble, he will moſt certainly deſtroy the proud, to qualifie the rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their pride, and to cure them of the Pluriſie of it, I queſtion not but God will give them ſtrength and ſucceſs to be their Phyſicians, to make them bleed for it. A good cauſe does wonders, thoſe Ships cannot miſcarry that are driven with the breath of good Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and with wiſdome, good conduct, and courage. If we ſhelter our ſelves under the ſhadow of the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, we are ſure to be poſſeſs'd of a moſt impregnable Fortreſs, a Hold, that will certainly hold, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deluded in our Truſts. A Common-wealth's too neer us. I hope that the State of Affairs there, their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59244:14"/>States General, and their general State too, may in a ſhort time admit of a better form of Government; if not, I wiſh with all my heart that I might but live to ſee them reduc'd to their firſt Principles; to be once more ſtyl'd, <hi>The poor diſtreſſed States.</hi> They have an old Proverb amongſt them which has none of the beſt Omens,
<q>
                  <l>Thoſe that bring themſelves into needleſs dangers,</l>
                  <l>Dye the Divel's Martyrs.</l>
               </q> And I doubt not but we ſhall bring their Spirits down, even as low as their Country: Here are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Amulets, Golden Engines, to draw and incline the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the People to their King, <hi>ad Arcendas noxas alicui corporis parti, &amp; collo alligantur;</hi> ye are ſecure enough, and when ye have ſo much kindneſs hang'd about your necks, me thinks ye ſhould be hang'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye leave him.</p>
            <p>Having made Digreſſion, <hi>rem ipſam jam aggrediar;</hi> Not long before His Majeſties Reſtauration, it was my fortune caſually to be in Company with a Chyrurgeon, who moſt audaciouſly and peremptorily vaunted, <hi>That he could never cure the</hi> King's Evil, <hi>till he had poſſeſſed himſelf with ſome of His Majeſties Lands:</hi> It was an Article in His Atheiſtical Creed, <hi>That this virtue went along with them, though in his undue poſſeſſions.</hi> I am yet to learn of any that ever yet adventured upon it, upon this Account, or that ever he experimentally found that ſucceſs, never any yet proſpered in Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion; God alwayes will withdraw his Bleſſing from the bloody Hand. From the Influence of a good King, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtils
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59244:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Balm that cures the Kings Evil; how many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in a year does he invite to draw neer to him? amongſt whom probably ſome are admitted, that he might moſt juſtly have commanded, rather a diſtance, who, when time was, would have laid their hands heavy upon him, had not God prevented it; Nevertheleſs, he is pleas'd to forget it, and lay his more tenderly upon them: Oh! may he in a more peculiar manner, be ſucceſsful unto them, had he the Spirit of diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, yet his goodneſs is ſuch, that he would not withdraw his helping hand from them, like a true An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of God, he does Good for Evil; he freely accepts them, and relieves them in their neceſſities, is kind to his worſt foes, and remits, like an Excellent Prince and a good Chriſtian, the wrong they have at any time done him: Nay, thoſe that would not do him ſo much right, as to afford him their Aſſiſtance to help him to his, do not bluſh to claim an inherent right, to this Priviledge, nay they ſuppoſe themſelves born to it, though him, not long ſince, to nothing.</p>
            <p>Me thinks they ſhould be diffident of a bleſſing; yet ſince they have ſo much eſteem for their King, and that through his good fortunes he is credulous, may he be fortunate in the higheſt degree; they may reſt ſatisfied, that God has endued him with ſo much power, as to effect this ſo great and eminent a work; may they live to have juſt Cauſe to repent them, that they have ſo evilly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him.</p>
            <p>May they ſhew their Contrition, by living as becomes Loyal Subjects, then they ſhall not want my prayers, that God may wipe away that bloud which lies upon them; <hi>Beneficium poſtulat Officium;</hi> Every benefit that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59244:15"/>we receive from our King, doth challenge a duty at our hands. Not long ſince, all humane Learning was trampled under feet; His Return has bleſs'd us with the Reſurrection of it. Before, we had many Lords, that vaunted much of Religion, but they divided it into ſo many Sects, and Errours, nay Blaſphemies, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the neceſſity of their Evil deſigns, and policy, led them, that one might well have asked, what the Religion of <hi>England</hi> was? But bleſſed be God that has reſtor'd our Princes as at the firſt, and our Counſellors as at the Beginning; <hi>Novares, nova cantica,</hi> for new mercies, we muſt find new praiſes. God has reſtor'd us to the Life of our Life, our Liberties and our Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions; before, there were great pretences of Laws and a free born people, and what not; and theſe were, 'tis true, neceſſary to thoſe that had no Title: We ſtand before God this day, the Subjects of many Bleſſings; being under the Power and Juriſdiction of an imparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd Prince, <hi>Carendo magis quàm habendo,</hi> by the want of a King we ſhould know the better how to value him; not to be thankful for him, and Gods mercies to us in it, is the death and deſtruction of mercies; not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them, is as it were to make them our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. I would have them well husbanded, that they might be Reſervations to greater mercies. As our thankfulneſs muſt appear in our Obedience towards God, ſo it muſt in our Obedience towards our King. <hi>Great Britain's Oake,</hi> had an immature, untimely fall, and yet there was one Royal one preſerv'd to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector to Him. <hi>Regis &amp; Regni Robor Robur,</hi> may we be loving to the Branch, though we were unfaithful to the Root. A Day of Special Deliverance, calls for a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59244:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Day of Thankſgiving. His Majeſty took too long a Progreſs in other Princes Dominions, but that the great Divinity thought good to have it ſo, now he may take one in His Own Kingdom. And 'twas once ſuppoſed, that after His great and miraculous Conqueſt of Reſtauration, He would have viſited that place of <hi>Worceſter.</hi> God would have been pleaſed with ſuch a Sacrifice: But alas! he has ſcarce yet had a Vacation from Perſecution. The firſt thing that <hi>Theſeus</hi> did, after the Victories over his Enemies, was to ſacrifice the Spoils to the Tutelar Gods. As <hi>Hercules</hi> wore the <hi>Lyon</hi>'s Skin, as a <hi>Memorandum</hi> of his Victories, ſo may His Majeſty, as an Addition to His Royal Coat, though never wear it out of His Memory, nor we neither, as an Emblem of that great and wonderful deliverance, <hi>The Royal-Oke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To perpetuate the remembrance of which, I wiſh in that very place an Hoſpital or Chappel were erected, and Demeaſnes for the maintenance of it, where there might be an Annual ſolemn Proceſſion. I would not have this done by His Majeſties Own Hand, but to His Hand by the publique Stock, as an acknowledgement to the King of Kings, for that unſpeakable mercy in the preſervation of Ours. Perhaps I may have the Return of a ſevere cenſure for offering thus far: yet it cannot be ſaid that I interpoſe in a buſineſſe wherein I am not concern'd, for I conjecture my ſelf as much as any, and could His Majeſty but be ſenſible of the thouſandth part of the Paſſion, which I have ever had (I bleſs God for it) and ſolely for Him, I ſhould have Pardon from Him, for taking this Freedom. He is the Ocean from whence flows thoſe Rivulets of good Will, which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59244:16"/>in Gratitude, like them, would oblige us to make our Returns. <hi>Gratitudo eſt Gratiarum Actio,</hi> not a bare Thanks-ſaying, but a Thanks-giving: we cannot do too much for him that has done ſo much for us; he has ſtanched that Iſſue of Blood under which we ſo long groan'd, and has made it his work to bring us into acquaintance with Peace, and Proſperity: will we be thankfull for theſe, and why not for health? Prayers and Praiſes ought to be alwayes like the Angels of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Ladder, aſcending and deſcending. When you approach His Majeſties preſence, in tendency to the work in hand, go the right way, and you'l be ſure not to fail of your end. Say with holy <hi>David', his thy work O Lord, not mans power; Thy ſacred Inſtitution, not mans Invention.</hi> It has been a queſtion in the Scholes, <hi>An liceat uti verbis ad morbos pellendos?</hi> It ſhall now be put out of diſpute, for God has promiſed that what ſoever we ſhall ask in his name by Divine ejaculations ſhall be done unto us. Behold the modeſty of His Sacred Majeſty in the very Act expreſs'd, <hi>Deus ſanat omnes infirmitates noſtras,</hi> I Touch and God heals: No charm like this Divine Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the Lips of the King, words worthy to be written in Letters of Gold, with the Pen of a Diamond, full of attractions, and ſecret allurements, and like the ſpirit of ſo Holy and ſo Magnificent a Prince; he does not aſſume the honour to himſelf, for fear of Cancelling that never to be forgotten Gift, vouchſafed him by God, in which he is made, next and immediate to him, the ſole inſtrument to do good to his people. What can ſatisfie more, that when he has done things <hi>ſuper captum rationis humanae, ſuper omnem doctrinam divinitus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum,</hi> 'tis ſupernatural, an Art that lyes above the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59244:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>reach of every Brain: Divine myſteries are not to be meaſured by the ſhort Plummet of humane Reaſon, our Underſtandings are much too ſhallow to fathome them. <hi>Magnalia Deiſumma &amp; miraculosè conſpiciuntur;</hi> Let us not pry into the Ark of God's Secrets, 'tis too preſumptuous Arrogancy in any, to queſtion that which was never yet revealed. The <hi>Royal Hand</hi> is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with God's Hand, he approves it by many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, which exceed the condition of Law and Nature; what He does ſhould beget a firm belief in us, and 'twere Impiety for a Chriſtian in the leaſt to doubt it; when 'tis done by his never-failing power, ſtop thy over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bold Enquiries, with a <hi>Deus ſic voluit.</hi> Yet there are too many that will not truſt Faith on her ſingle Bond, unleſs Reaſon be joyn'd for Security with her. The Subſtance of Hope is the Being of Beings, our being well, 'tis no ſhadow, here Faith is no fancy, there muſt be reality in it, ſince 'tis not exerciſed in a deluſory work, which not to credit, is, in a degree, a kind of Blaſphemy. Is any thing hard to God Almighty? He is not like unto him that promiſeth and performeth not, wait for him in this ſerious and ſolemn Ceremony, and he will certainly come and heal thee. Hitherto the Touch has been ſolely touch'd upon, eſpecially that from the hand of His Sacred Majeſty, in which there is ſo much efficacy, That I want Charity, to be reconcil'd to the Philoſopher, that aſſerted <hi>Tactum</hi> to be <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem,</hi> and inſerted it in the Rear of all the Senſes; it ſhall have my Vote for the future, to have the Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in our new Phyloſophy. I ſhall now entreat upon the Gift, as well as the Giver, being indeed Individual, and then I muſt be in Conſult with Angels, good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59244:17"/>good Gold. The Bleſſings of the Father of our Country: <hi>Aurum cum primis efficax praeſentiſſimam vim obtinet, in expugnandis ſaeviſſimis morbis, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randâ valetudine ubi collapſa eſt;</hi> which introduces a Story of that moſt experienced perſon Doctor <hi>Butler</hi> of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> who being ſent for to the Earl of <hi>Lincoln</hi>'s Son, finding him deſperate ill of a malignant Fever, and ſpeechleſs; As ſoon as he came into the Chamber, he calls to the good old Earl for Gold; he was a great Humoriſt, His mind to him a kingdom was; at length that dumb God Gold appear'd: The Doctor, inſtead of putting it into his pocket, as thoſe that knew him not, might very well have ſuſpected, crams as many pieces into his Patient's mouth as it would well contain: At which ſight, ſayes the good Earl, <hi>If he will eat Gold, Doctor, he ſhall have it, but beware good Doctor you do not choke my Child;</hi> continuing a while in his mouth, they came out as black as a Coal. The malignity thus ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it ſelf, the Gentleman recovered, ſo that you ſee <hi>Regina Pecunia Quid non?</hi> what wonders Gold will do; She ſits Queen Regent at the helm of all Affairs, made him to ſpeak that would not ſpeak before. Gold, by the Impreſs of its purity, does <hi>omnem à corpore impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem dejicere;</hi> Angel Gold, does <hi>ſpiritus foetidos ſpirare, &amp; vi quadam attractrice pollere;</hi> once in the boſome, 'tis a good friend, and being tried by that veſtal Fire, muſt needs do him good at heart that has it. Some think, that if they have but a Touch from the King, they are preſently made whole, their work is at an end; they are to begin again: Some ſay, they care not if they get a Touch; but touch not upon that ſtring with ſo much indifferency, ſuch Approaches marr
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59244:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Succeſs, though Angels, and good ones, attend the Service. There muſt be <hi>Auri ſacra fames,</hi> when 'tis <hi>Aurum vitae,</hi> and infinite Reſtorative, <hi>habet ſpiritum ſecretiſſimum, &amp; coeleſtem imaginem Dei gerens;</hi> if ſo, no Crucifix more potent. May the celeſtial powers, the whole Hierarchy of Angels, that never ſlumber nor ſleep, be our Soveraign's Life-guard; they can obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate all approaching Evils, and help Him, and protect Him, in and under ſo ſoveraign a diſpenſation, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with His Prerogative; let this be the Return of our loudeſt praiſes, that we give Glory to God on High, fear Him, and honour our King. And that ye may be ſure to find benefit in your Addreſſes, let this be the Rule, Make not your deſires the ſole Rule of your Prayers, but ſubmit your Wills to God's Will; that's a duty incumbent upon you. Prayers have wings for flying, without fear of falling: Say with good <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah, Heal me, O Lord, and I ſhall be healed.</hi> Though the difficulties are many, yet Faith, which hath a kind of an Impotency will carry you through all. <hi>Ille plures ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, de quo plures confidunt;</hi> The Sick man's confidence, oft-times ſpeeds beyond all other remedies, <hi>confidentia &amp; alacrilas morbos ſublevat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Noble Greek gave not that name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for nought, <hi>quaſi baſis</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>quod in Rege ſalus populi fundata eſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Virtue and Regal Excellency meet for ſuch a Prince, it adds Luſtre to His Royal Perſon, and makes Him the more Conſpicuous and Illuſtrious in the Eyes of all His People. Some are of that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the Commonneſs of the Gift, makes it to be diſ-eſteemed; Yet, <hi>bonum, tanto eſt melius, quanto eſt communius.</hi> God will not unmake his Miracles, by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59244:18"/>making them common. May we be heartily affected with the true ſenſe of God's mercy to us in it, otherwiſe we make it but a formal Complement, which will not be approved of by him from whom it is firſt deriv'd; you have the Hands of God and a King hand in hand, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centrating in one, and employed as Supraviſors of the work. There is ſo conſtant a Communication betwixt them, that 'tis impoſſible but to effect any thing. A good and pious Prince we have, a King that drop'd down unexpectedly from Heaven, whoſe works are without compare. When a Man does that which ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cannot do, we uſually ſay <hi>He conjures;</hi> pardon I pray the Expreſſion: That Magick is laudable and lawful, where there is not <hi>Potentia in nocendo ſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituendo.</hi> He is an Object for Love and Wonder to ſtand amazed at.</p>
            <p>The Geſture, when we come to receive theſe <hi>Bona Throni vel Scabelli,</hi> is kneeling, which denotes true humility and reverence, and that we ought to pay to him ſome Tribute from our Bodies. God payes us well for our pains, and ſends an Angel home with us: <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea remedia,</hi> we have golden rewards. <hi>Myſerium hoe celandum,</hi> were it not that the effects daily prove ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; nothing weakens a man's confidence like Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, the calling to mind of which, fills the heart with diffidence. Let us ſpeak of Him as becomes us, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently imitating the Tongues of the Apoſtles, with holy Language; he deſerves it at our hands. The comforts we receive, and particular pledges of true kindneſs from Him, ſhould, me-thinks, beget the re-inforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of love, proportionable to his merits. And let me tell you, that he differs only from the Angels, rather
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59244:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>in place, than condition, becauſe he has conferr'd on him while on Earth, a portion of Heaven, Angelical Gifts. He is a Prince of eaſie acceſs and a patient ear, and patent, indefatigable in hearing us, one that does not expoſtulate why we come at any time to give him trouble, becauſe he thinks it none, ſupereminent Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies conveyed us. <hi>Loves Envoies and Amour vaine tout fors que coeur felon,</hi> Love overcomes any thing but a froward or deſpiteful heart. If we will not be like our ſelves, may we be like the <hi>Sabine</hi> women, with love and Interceſſion which conquered two Armies, a Victory more eminent then the Sword can win, and none ſurer than the Victory of Prayer. When you go to celebrate this Myſterie, let not your mind be like an <hi>Individuum vagum;</hi> if it be, 'tis but meer Lip-labour, a ſacrifice as unacceptable, as that of <hi>Cain</hi>'s. If you make your addreſſes amiſs, wonder not if you miſs, 'tis all the odds as may be, but you will: Prayer is the Key that opens the gates of heaven, 'tis the never-failing means of bringing thee, if not all that thou thinkeſt thou wanteſt, yet all indeed thou doſt. Let your affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions be as ſtrong as your faith. But what's the reaſon then, ſay ſome, that ſo many Infants and young Children, that have not the leaſt ſence of faith, in them, have redreſs in their addreſſes? You ſhall have my ſenſe upon it, 'Tis becauſe they are the Children of true believing Parents, and 'tis impoſſible the Children of ſo many Prayers and Tears ſhould be ineffectual, or return without a bleſſing: The Prayer of the humble pierceth the Clouds, and will not admit of the leaſt <hi>Iot a</hi> of denial, till the Higheſt accompliſh their deſires; 'tis like <hi>Saul</hi>'s Sword, and <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s Bow, never returns
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59244:19"/>empty. Make not your approaches to your King, for Company, or Faſhious ſake, as too many do, but with a true acknowledgement that God is the great ſpring from whence the benefit muſt flow, he is much deceived that truſteth too much to himſelf; where too much conſidence is in the means, you thruſt out God, who muſt not be an unconcerned Spectator of humane affairs, he is worth the care of ingaging him on your ſide. Pray not more to the Chyrurgeon for acceſs, then to God for ſucceſs; gratifie them where you find kindneſs, but let not your Fees fly faſter then your Prayers.</p>
            <p>Do you expect good by it, doubt of your own wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs; there is none wanting in the King. This bleſſed Myſterie ſo graciouſly diſpenſed by God's Vicegerent here upon Earth, cannot but be ſow'd in ſufficient power; if there be weakneſs and folly in them that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to receive it, if you vacate the Gift, and fruſtrate the intent of the Donor, 'tis not the Kings ſault, nor ought to be laid to his charge, charge your ſelves with it. When relief does come, it does not alwayes come in that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of time when the Touch is vouchſafed. There muſt be obedience to him that Toucheth, aſwel as belief in him to approve it by. Of thoſe ten in the Goſpel that were cleanſed of their Leproſie, there came but one to pay his thanks, yet I fear there is not one in ten hundred, though he receives as much benefit as he can poſſibly deſire, that comes with his acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; may he do it to God, and pay his Allegiance to his King: Nay, 'tis credibly reported of a Gentlewoman, that Seventeen years after ſhe had received what her own heart could wiſh for, from the hand of that good King, who did us all good, though we did him all harm,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59244:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>(whom I cannot mention without tears, and a Preface of all due honour and reſpect) ſhe ſent her Angel to <hi>Goldſmiths-hall,</hi> to be employed againſt him; This was a peice of high unthankfulneſs, and ought to have had a better requital. Great Ingratitude, great puniſhment; How juſt had it been with God Almighty to have brought upon her, as a ſcourge for ſo much wickedneſs, a Recidivation of former accidents, nay, worſe than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, more contumacious and Rebellious, like her ſelf? ſhe had been payed in her own Coin, and had a reward ſuitable to her merits. <hi>Oh Temporal! Oh Mores!</hi> when injuſtice and contempt of all truth and honeſty was juſtified, when Rebellion was brought into countenance and made the mode and faſhion of the times, which ought never to be upon record; he that ſhall leave them to poſterity, if without partiality he writes them, he will certainly have as much water in his Eyes, as Ink in his Pen, wherein lived a Generation of curſed <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phels,</hi> which dreaded the ſingularity of being innocent. They found a new gate to heaven, not opened before, to cut their way thither through the throats of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate; Subjects ſhould be Adjectives, not able to ſtand without (much leſs againſt) their Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or they will make but bad conſtruction; <hi>Had</hi> Zimri <hi>peace, that ſlew his Maſter?</hi> Oh Lord! keep us by thy reſtraining grace from going along with the rude multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, by ſeeming to right the People, though wrong the King. Let us pray for him as well in times of quiet as of danger, as well when War is but ſmoaking, as when 'tis blown into a flame. Let us be conſtant and not given to change. 'Tis Treaſon <hi>ſummo gradu,</hi> in the higheſt malignity, to lay the calamity of the People up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59244:20"/>on the Prince, as if the Diſeaſe begun in the head, when properly it terminates there. A King that fore-caſts and fore-cares, I am confident, to make you all the better for him, what horrible injuſtice will it be in you to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure him? I wiſh the very Heathen may not riſe up in judgement againſt you; They were praying for their Emperours, though condemned by them, in the midſt of the flames, <hi>Every man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>ſhould be a friend to him that giveth Gifts;</hi> he is greatly ours, his favour is as <hi>Aurora's</hi> dew, which purleth the ſpangled graſs; ſuch innate ſeeds are ſown in him, as will ever improve him, never deprave him: Behold him as one, <hi>In quo virtutes omnes elucent, &amp; quem colere nihil aliud eſt, quàm virtutes ipſas colere;</hi> to reverence him, without flattery, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but to adore his vertues. Let us receive his Commands, as if they came from heaven, and behave our ſelves towards him, with due obſervance, and not, upon any pretence of infirmity whatſoever, contemn him. God has moſt miraculouſly own'd him amongſt the ſtorms of State and War; he has ſail'd through a boundleſs Sea of bliſs, <hi>Si inſuperabilis inſeperabilis.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion is like Fire from above, infinite deſtructive; mens conſtitutions and their ſpirits were volatile, but now I hope God has fix'd them, and will keep thoſe qualities in a right temper and juſt Symmetry amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. A true Princely diſpoſition, moderated with ſo many inward qualifications, as meekneſs, ſobriety, and indeed what not? merits the whole Trump and ſound commendation and applauſe above all other. He is one whom I could dwell upon to admire, and loſe my ſelf in the Maze: Yet <hi>Tantus quiſque eſt quantus eſt apud Deum;</hi> Every one is ſo great as he is in Gods account;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59244:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>but to be Good and Great is admirable. Let it not be made a crime to do good; Charity may legally be Acted without purchaſing Licence <hi>ad practicandum.</hi> You may ſee we have more Gifts than one from him, we had a common deed of Gift, of General Pardon, of which we are moſt unworthy, if we do not every day grow better and better, if we are not the better for mercies, we muſt be the worſe. A good Chriſtian muſt inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be a good Subject; I muſt confeſs I have one quality in me, for which I have been blamed by many, though in my own apprehenſion I conceive it none of the worſt, which is, that I cannot be in good earneſt in Charity, with any that ever went out, but to fight againſt their King; ſome to this day are ſo obſtinate, that they will uſe Arguments to palliate, as if 'twere poſſible to exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate, that great and crying abomination, that horrid Murther of their King, ſo notoriouſly committed; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick acknowledgement with Godly ſorrow for it, were the only balm to expiate: when 'tis urg'd againſt them, they have this Plea in a readineſs to retort, That they went not out to fight againſt him, but to draw him from his evil Councel. They knew their King was forced to open hoſtility, and to ſet up his Royal Standard <hi>Se defendendo,</hi> and try his Title. Alas, will ſome ſay, we broke off in good time; They had ſo indeed, had they not firſt broke the Ice (the more Capital their crime) and then broke out into open Rebellion. Would they have acquitted themſelves fairly? Why did they not then, when they heard their King and ſuch a Lord and Maſter was in the Feild, but that they intended, as plainly ſince has appeared, to be His; Why did they not then, I ſay, throw down their Arms and themſelves at His Majeſties
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59244:21"/>feet, and pay their Allegiance to him, that he might gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly have received them into His? They had juſt cauſe to do it.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that adventur'd at the beginning of the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion their lives and fortunes to preſerve their King, his Heirs and Succeſſors in their juſt Rights; thoſe were the men, thoſe were thoſe that were right and true Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, too many of them have been ſince ſufferers indeed, and only upon the ſcore of Loyalty, for whom I have a very particular regard, becauſe I ſee them by ſome ſo little regarded. His Majeſty is ſo gracious of himſelf, that he has own'd many of them, and would more, were there not thoſe that interpoſe too much betwixt the beams of that favour and grace, which probably have not themſelves deſerv'd it, ſome have been and are countenanced too much, few as they ought; ſo that in the opinion of thoſe, they are like old Almanacks out of date, or ſtand for Ciphers. I muſt confeſs, as 'tis well known, I have been zealous for the poor caſt-away Chavalry, for which I have received often reproof and checks, and meerly for ſpeaking but my conſcience in their behalf, and have had it retorted upon me with the greateſt wonder, that one that was never in Arms for His Majeſty, ſhould be ſo earneſt to gratifie men that would never be ſatisfied; But I cannot be of that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion. 'Tis true, I was not in Arms for him, yet I bleſs God for it t<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, and for nothing almoſt more, than that I never was againſt him; yet 'tis probable I have done him no leſs ſervice, then ſome that were with him, the truth of all which others enough can aſſert, and I have retained within me, without the leaſt ſtain, that principle becoming both an honeſt man and a good Subject, Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59244:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>to my now Soveraign and his Father of ever bleſſed Memory before him, and in the worſt of times, durſt maintain their Prerogatives; and I ſuppoſe ſuch are none of the worſt Subjects. My aid, God willing, ſhall never be wanting to caſt a mite into his Treaſury, and without Oſtentation I ſpeak it, and upon Review it will appear, that I have upon all occaſions contributed, beyond in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed what I have, and have exceeded many, that have far exceeded me in eſtate. Thus I have done with as ſincere Devoires as any Hee that His Majeſty is pleaſed to have the beſt thoughts of; I have done but my Duty in it, and I ſhall not forget to do that ſtill, unleſs a Lethargie poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs my Brain; All I have, as I do, in good earneſt, own from his Sacred Majeſty, ſo I ſhall chearfully be ready to proſtrate it at his feet, with my life into the bargain for Him or His, whom I eſteem your Royal Highneſs.</p>
            <p>Scrue up all his Majeſties Actions, and you will find them miracles, celebrate his praiſes beyond what thoſe of men, might or ought to aſpire to, and though he Touch the Evil, may no Evil touch him. Let not the gates of Hell prevail againſt him. My unfeigned and unceſſant Prayers ſhall ever (God willing) attend him; and my curſes, thoſe that wiſh him worſe than their own ſouls. Thoſe that will not ſay Amen to it, deſerve to be hang'd, I pray God they be not damn'd. And may there never want one from that Royal Stem to govern us, and Sway the Scepter to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>And now, Royal Sir, may all your Atchievements be crown'd with Victory. May you have more Friends than Flatterers. The greateſt hope I have of ſucceſs in this grand affair lyes in the juſtneſs of our Cauſe, the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and abundant care of his Majeſty for our preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59244:22"/>the prudence and courage of your Highneſs: That benevolent aſpect which hath raiſed the general love of all to you, doth in this occurrence incline the great ones, the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Chivalry</hi> of the whole Nation to wait upon you: thoſe hearts your Highneſs lately car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with you, were not at ſuch a loſs as we were then for your abſence, nor expected you with more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience. At ſuch a ſeaſon the ſtouteſt might well have been weary of ſuch Service. Fortitude in a Prince, is a vertue, true, but dangerous, ſhould you miſcarry we are at a loſs irreparable. Great Sir, we have fraught this our little Veſſel with Commodities of no ſmall price. If theſe notions hold water, as I hope they will, there will be no great fear of Leaking, The more fit and ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Preſent, to preſent ſuch an Admiral. Such a one it is as may do wonders: the greateſt conqueſt is that of hearts and affections. Theſe take as Plots upon all the forces both by Sea and Land, to re-inforce them, if poſſible, to that which has been too long at too low an Ebbe: In this caſe, to promote Love, is an Art very lawful and juſtifiable both before God and Man. This Tract is calculated exactly to this Meridian, and deſign'd on purpoſe, as a Specifique and Soveraign Antidote, defenſive furniture againſt the ſudden incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon the Palace-Royal, and that never-enough to be deteſted Sin, which fretteth like a Gangreen, and menaceth to eat out the Life and Soul of Monarchy and Religion, <hi>Rebellion.</hi> Undoubtedly, to effect this, is none of the worſt piece of Service, but a very good piece; and if ſo, I ſhall think my pains well ſpent, and have the leſs regard to Cenſure: No times have ever yet vouchſafed to the worthieſt of Perſonages, an immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59244:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>from malignant Tongues, 'twere Vanity therefore in me to expect it. To endevour but a publique good ever yet merited a <hi>Commendum,</hi> though not ſo well perform'd as really intended; and this give me leave to ſay, He muſt needs have a ſtrange vitiated Palate to whom none of theſe will Reliſh. This Tract is but of yeſterday, as 'tis ſhort, ſo 'tis ſweet, breathing forth odoriferous and moſt fragrant vapours into the Noſtrils of all that are truly Loyal; and I wiſh 'twere like the <hi>Manna</hi> in the Wilderneſs, which adapts it ſelf to every Man's <hi>Guſto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having touch'd long upon a Golden Subject, the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal being tryed by the Touchſtone of your Highneſſe's moſt Gracious Acceptance, I have abundantly my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and for attempting to <hi>deſerve</hi> your favour, I hope I ſhall not <hi>diſſerve</hi> my Prince, to whom, I am not more by Conſcience bound, than I ſhall, through all the Actions of my Life, ever own a particular Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to expreſs my humble duty. Having treſpaſſed thus much upon your Highneſſe's Patience, 'tis high time to turn my Sailes towards the Shore, and caſt Anchor for the Preſent: <hi>Eadem magnanimitate quâ magna mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera donas parva munuſcula accipe;</hi> it hath been a Grace for Greatneſs, at mean men's hands, to accept of ſmall Gifts.</p>
            <p>If this chance to have the Honor to kiſs His Majeſty's moſt Sacred Hand, 'tis more than the Authour has yet had himſelf; if it arrives to that, he has his end; and the <hi>Errata's,</hi> and <hi>Evil</hi> in it, will admit of a perfect Cure.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
